Guide to the Gary Indiana Papers 1976-2005 MSS.168
Fales Library and Special Collections
Gary Indiana Papers
1976-2005
Fales Library and Special Collections
Indiana, Gary
MSS.168
13 Linear Feet (27 boxes)
The Gary Indiana Papers are comprised of materials which document the literary career of Gary Indiana. Collection materials include manuscripts, galleys, diaries, notebooks, correspondence, contracts, postcards, flyers, theater programs, periodical and newspaper clippings, photographs, collages, and posters.
Provenance
The Gary Indiana Papers were purchased from Gary Indiana in 2005.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Gary Indiana (real name Gary Hoisington) was born in 1950 and brought up in Derry, New Hampshire. He and an older brother were raised by his parents, Cecile and Carol Hoisington. In his twenties, he moved to Berkeley and changed his name to Indiana. After two years, Indiana relocated to Boston, where he worked in various capacities before returning to California, this time to Los Angeles where he wrote for punk zines. After a 1974 car accident, he decided to leave for New York, where he became immersed in the downtown arts scene.
In the 1980s, Indiana wrote for Artforum and Art in America, among other magazines. He also acted in a number of German and American films, notably working with Dieter Schidor and other members of Rainer Werner Fassbinder's circle. From 1984 onward, Indiana wrote art criticism for the Village Voice, establishing the uncompromising journalistic style that would become his trademark. During this time he was also very active in the theater, working closely with Bill Rice and Taylor Mead, among others, in both his own plays and others'. Notable plays by Indiana include Alligator Girls Go to College (1979), Curse of the Dog People (1980), Phantoms of Louisiana (1981), The Roman Polanski Story (1981), and Roy Cohn/Jack Smith (1992).
In the late '80s, Indiana published two short story collections, Scar Tissue and Other Stories (1987) and White Trash Boulevard (1988), immediately followed by his first novel, Horse Crazy (1989). In addition to his critical writing, Indiana published novels throughout the 1990s, often writing fictionalized accounts of real-life murder cases like that of Andrew Cunanan in 1999's Three Month Fever.
Indiana continues to publish fiction work and write for a variety of publications on art, film, literature, and politics. The Guardian has called Indiana "one of the most important chroniclers of the American psyche."
Missing Title
Shanghai (1983)
The Role of My Family in the World Revolution (1985)
Scar Tissue and Other Stories (1987)
White Trash Boulevard (1988)
Horse Crazy (1989)
Gone Tomorrow (1993)
Rent Boy (1994)
Living with the Animals (1995) (Ed. by Gary Indiana)
Let It Bleed: Essays 1985-1995 (1996)
Resentment: A Comedy (1997)
Three Month Fever: The Andrew Cunanan Story (1999)
Salò or The 120 Days of Sodom (2000)
Depraved Indifference (2002)
Do Everything in the Dark (2003)
The Schwarzenegger Syndrome: Politics and Celebrity in the Age of Contempt (2005)
Missing Title
Custody (1979)
Alligator Girls Go To College (1979)
Curse of the Dog People (1980)
The Dark Side of Anne Flaubert (1980)
Phantoms of Louisiana (1981)
The Roman Polanski Story (1981)
Return of the Dog People (1984)
Roy Cohn (1992)
Who Killed Rex the Wonder Dog?
A Thwarted Sense of Occasion
Scope and Content Note
The Gary Indiana Papers are comprised of manuscripts, galleys, diaries, notebooks, correspondence, contracts, postcards, flyers, theater programs, periodical and news clippings, magazines, published materials, snapshots, photographs, collages, and posters.
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS
SERIES I: Manuscripts
Subseries A contains manuscripts for novels and fiction writing, as well as novel proposals. Novel manuscripts include Rent Boy, partial drafts of Gone Tomorrow, and the unpublished Desert Shore. Short fiction manuscripts include The Role of My Family in the World Revolution, a fragment of Shanghai, and numerous unpublished pieces. Galley proofs for White Trash Boulevard are located in the Oversize series [Folder 11].
Subseries B contains theatrical and cinematic manuscripts. Some theatrical manuscripts are actors' typescripts for Indiana's productions. Also included is a script not by Indiana for Dieter Schidor's 1985 film Cold in Columbia, in which Indiana appeared.
Subseries C contains poetry and lyrics written and sung for the band The Boners. Some poetry is dated by Indiana. Some prose is also included as part of a grouping created and dated by Indiana.
Subseries D contains critical essays, interview notes, and some miscellaneous manuscript materials. Interview notes include Chantal Akerman, David Lynch, and Carol Ross. Also included is the checklist for Indiana's 2002 photography retrospective "Extinction" at American Fine Arts, Co. in New York City.
SERIES II: Journals
Subseries A contains drafts and notes for novels and essays, personal journals, travel diaries, and assorted research notes. The dated notebooks range from 1981 to 2003.
Subseries B contains collage notebooks and sketchbooks, some of which includes Indiana's photography.
SERIES III: Correspondence and Legal Documents
The correspondence series consists of personal and professional correspondence. Personal correspondence includes letters and postcards from figures including musician and poet Patti Smith and artist Valie Export, among others. Professional correspondence consists of publishing contracts and rights agreements with HarperCollins and other publishing companies. Also included is the report of the court examination of Indiana in his lawsuit against The Bar. Some postcard correspondence is contained in the Flyers and Visual Materials Series [Series IVA] as part of Indiana's flyer and program scrapbook. A poster from the Patti Smith correspondence is located in the Oversize series.
SERIES IV: Flyers and Visual Materials
Subseries A consists of the contents of a scrapbook, organized by Indiana, of programs and flyers for events or performances by himself and others. Some postcard correspondence is also included in the scrapbook. Also included are materials not associated with this scrapbook: one folder of event flyers and a flyer for the 1980 Times Square Show, the latter being in the Oversize series [Folder 124].
Subseries B consists of assorted visual materials, including publication artwork for several of Indiana's novels, photographs of work by Bill Rice, a calendar entitled "Men of The Bar," collage materials and miscellaneous artwork.
SERIES V: Printed Materials
This series consists of published materials, including books, theatre programs, and periodicals, many of which include Indiana's writing or writing about Indiana. One issue of Night (no. 52) has been moved to the Oversize series [Folder 161].
SERIES VI: Clippings
Subseries A consists of clippings of art criticism, essays, and other items written by Indiana. This includes substantial criticism written for the Village Voice, Artforum, and Art in America, among other publications.
Subseries B consists of clippings of writing about Indiana or reviews of his published works.
Subseries C consists of clippings used as research materials, including those regarding Henri Cartier-Bresson, Witold Gombrowicz, and Valie Export, among others.
SERIES VII: Photography
Subseries A contains Indiana's 4 x 5 snapshots, including documentation of the Toronto Film Festival premiere of David Cronenberg's Naked Lunch, The Dazzling 1987 New York Flower Show, trips to Latin America, downtown New York City street scenes, and a New York gallery opening and party. Also included are evidence photos from the Andrew Cunanan case, the basis for Indiana's novel Three Month Fever.
Subseres B contains 5 x 7 snapshots of a wide array of subjects, including trips to Latin America, Cuba, India, and many regions of the United States. Also included are photos of a reading by actors Taylor Mead and Bill Rice, Indiana and others, an exhibit at the Museum of Contemporary Art in La Jolla, California, and photos of The Bishop's School in La Jolla, from which Andrew Cunanan graduated in 1987. Figures documented prominently include Bill Rice, Taylor Mead, and author William S. Burroughs.
Subseries C contains Indiana's 8.5 x 11 photo series, retaining his original order and organization. Major series include travel photos, nudes, cemetery photos, digital collage work by Indiana, and contact sheets from the film Bangkok Talkie and the play The Roman Polanski Story.
Subseres D contains photography of varying sizes maintained in individual groupings created and sometimes labeled by Indiana.
Subseries E consists of two boxes of photographic slides, retaining Indiana's organization. Also included are several photographic negatives and one 4 x 5" transparency.
Subseries F contains oversize photographic items, including photos bearing the copyright of Digne Meller Marcowicz which mainly relate to Werner Schroeter and German theater productions.
SERIES VIII: Oversize
Oversize items comprise posters for a 2004 speaking date and the plays Alligator Girls Go to College and The Roman Polanski Story, and several photographic works. Also included are galley proofs of White Trash Boulevard from the Manuscripts series, and a signed Patti Smith poster entitled "You Can't Say 'Fuck' in Radio Free America," removed from her personal correspondence with Indiana. A 2005 issue of Night has been removed from the Printed Materials series.
An oversize poster for the 1980 Times Square Show, removed from the Flyers series, is located in the Mapcase.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in series according to material formats or the types of writing represented.
Within each series, materials are arranged chronologically, when material is dated. In some cases, which are indicated, material organized by Indiana has retained its original organization.
Missing Title
Series I: Manuscripts
Series II: Journals
Series III: Correpsondence and Legal Documents
Series IV: Flyers and Visual Materials
Series V: Printed Materials
Series VI: Clippings
Series VII: Photography and Snapshots
Oversize Items
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Between C & D Archive (MSS.084)
Dennis Cooper Papers (MSS.085)
Downtown Flyers and Invitations Collection (MSS.119)
Ron Kolm Papers (MSS.079)
Terence Sellers Papers (MSS.167)
Serpent's Tail/High Risk Books Archive (MSS.086)
Lynne Tillman Papers (MSS.180)
David Wojnarowicz Papers (MSS.092)
Separated Material
These materials have been separated from the archive and individually catalogued into the Downtown Book and Periodical Collection in Fales.
Missing Title
Aperture no. 127 (Spring 1992).
Artext no. 77 (Summer 2002).
Gober, Robert and Christopher Wool. A Project. April 1988.
Johnson, Larry. Larry Johnson. 1996.
Lehndorff, Vera and Holger Trulzsch. Oxydationen. 1985.
Purple Fashion no. 1 (Spring/Summer 2004).
Purple Fashion no. 3 (Spring/Summer 2005).
The Purple Journal no. 1 (Summer 2004). English version.
The Purple Journal no. 2 (Fall 2004). English version.
Le Purple Journal no. 2 (Fall 2004). French version.
The Purple Journal no. 3 (Winter 2005). English version.
Le Purple Journal no. 3 (Winter 2005). French version.
Le Purple Journal no. 4 (Spring 2005). French version.
The Purple Journal no. 5 (Summer 2005). English version.
Le Purple Journal no. 5 (Summer 2005). French version.
Rosenberg, Aura. Head Shots. New York: Stop Over Press, 1996.
Samaras, Lucas. Chairs and Drawings. New York: Pace Publications, 1987.
Texte Zur Kunst no. 15.57 (March 2005).
Wool, Christopher. Christopher Wool. New York: Scalo Publishers, 1998.
Artists and community -- United States; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Miami Beach (Fla.); La Jolla (San Diego, Calif.); Photographers -- United States.; Scripts (documents); Theater |z Germany.; Film criticism.; Experimental theater; Clippings (information artifacts); Scrapbooks.; Diaries; Correspondence.; South America.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Photographs.; Magazines (Periodicals); Avant-garde literature.; Avant-garde poetry.; New York (N.Y.).; New Delhi (India).; Poetry.; Art, American -- New York (State) -- New York.; Art criticism.; Reviews (document genre); Postcards.; Posters.; Artforum; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997; Art in America (Firm); High Risk Books (Firm); Rice, William, 1931-2006; Meller Marcovicz, Digne; Mead, Taylor; Kevorkian, Jack; Indiana, Gary; HarperCollins (Firm); Export, Valie; Cunanan, Andrew, 1969-1997; Versace, Gianni; Sobhraj, Charles; Schroeter, Werner, 1945-2010
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Subseries A: Manuscripts for Novels and Fiction
    Scope and Contents note
    Subseries A contains manuscripts for novels and fiction writing, as well as novel proposals. Novel manuscripts include Rent Boy, partial drafts of Gone Tomorrow, and the unpublished Desert Shore. Short fiction manuscripts include The Role of My Family in the World Revolution, a fragment of Shanghai, and numerous unpublished pieces. Galley proofs for White Trash Boulevard are located in the Oversize series [Folder 11].
    - Rent Boy original typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gone Tomorrow partial drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Desert Shore: A Novel (pp. 1-130), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Desert Shore: A Novel (pp. 131-260), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Desert Shore: A Novel (pp. 261-404), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Desert Shore: A Novel (partial drafts), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Maze: A Novel, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Big Other (unfinished novel and proposal), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gluttony (novel proposal), undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Ch. 2 of Unfinished Novel", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Shanghai (fragment)", undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - The Role of My Family in the World Revolution, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Dreams Involving Water drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Express, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - I Am Candy Jones, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Crisis in the Life of an Actor, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - One Size Fits All, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Philosophy in the Bedroom, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Only You, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Sympathy for Medea, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Valerie Solanas (The Revised SCUM Manifesto)", undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Misc. Fiction Manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Subseries B: Manuscripts for Plays and Film
    Contains theatrical and cinematic manuscripts. Some theatrical manuscripts are actors' typescripts for Indiana's productions. Also included is a script not by Indiana for Dieter Schidor's 1985 film Cold in Columbia, in which Indiana appeared.
    - Custody, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Alligator Girls Go To College, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Alligator Girls Go To College / Performed at Mudd Club Nov. 1979" (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Curse of the Dog People, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Curse of the Dog People (original version)", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Curse of the Dog People (original typescript)", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Bill Rice's typescript, w/ Photos / 'Curse of the Dog People'" [See Photography Series], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - The Dark Side of Anne Flaubert, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Phantoms of Louisiana, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - The Roman Polanski Story, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Return of the Dog People, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Roy Cohn, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Roy Cohn galleys for anthology", 1998 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Red Tide, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Red Tide [original typescript]", undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - A Thwarted Sense of Occasion, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Bangkok Talkie [film script], undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Unfinished/Incomplete Scripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Cold in Columbia [script by Dieter Schidor, feat. Indiana], undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Subseries C: Manuscripts for Poetry
    Contains poetry and lyrics written and sung for the band The Boners. Some poetry is dated by Indiana. Some prose is also included as part of a grouping created and dated by Indiana.
    - "Poems I + Lyrics written and sung for The Boners", undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "Poems II", undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Poems III", undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Poems IV / Short Prose (early + recent prose)", undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Misc. Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Subseries D: Manuscripts for Critical and Non-Fiction Writing
    Contains critical essays, interview notes, and some miscellaneous manuscript materials. Interview notes include Chantal Akerman, David Lynch, and Carol Ross. Also included is the checklist for Indiana's 2002 photography retrospective "Extinction" at American Fine Arts, Co. in New York City.
    - No Such Thing as Paranoia, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - A Culture High and Low, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Wegman Contra Landseer, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Charles Sobhraj writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Carol Ross conversation/writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "Proposal for Essay collection", undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - David Lynch interview transcript, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Chantal Akerman interview transcript, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Ingrid Caven interview materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - "Checklist for 'Extinction' Retrospective at American Fine Arts, Chelsea / Feb 2002", 2001 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Misc. Critical Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Series II: Journals
  - Subseries A: Diaries and Writing Journals
    Contains drafts and notes for novels and essays, personal journals, travel diaries, and assorted research notes. The dated notebooks range from 1981 to 2003.
    - "Notes from Brussels and Paris / Draft scenes for 'Phantoms of Louisiana'", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - "Parisian Notes / Camera coordinates for a screenplay", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Taste of the Black Earth ("Screenplay + scenario written in Paris w/ David Wojnarowicz"), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - "BURMA (Aug-Sept 85, Peterskirchen)", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - "Antigua Diary", 1989 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - New Orleans - Long Island, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - "Argentinian Diary", 1995 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Notes while writing 'Resentment' - Iguazu Argentina / Asuncion Paraguay", 1995 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - "Notes taken in Chile, Peru, Paraguay, Argentina and Bolivia", 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "Upstate New York", 1999 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - "Notes in Detroit while covering murder trial of Jack Kevorkian for the death of Thomas Hyde", [1999] (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - "Notes on the abandoned novel for St. Martins + diary entries", 2003 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - "Burma, Notes", undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - "Buenos Aires - Mendoza - Santiago - Peru - Bolivia - Paraguay - Brazil", undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Notes for 'Resentment', undated (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - "Monologue of the owner of O'Conquero in 'The Falls' in Do Everything in the Dark, location transplanted to Iguazu Falls", undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - "Los Angeles / Notes for 'The Big Other' / Notes for review of 'Black Dahlia Avenger'", undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - "Notes on the first Gulf War / Diary entry in New Orleans", undated (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - "Parisian Notes", undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - "Notes on Piglia + Argentina / New Delhi journals / Notes on Surrealism / Rent Boy listings on a phone service", undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - "Notes for a book about Charles Sobhraj, taken in New Delhi, Mumbai, Goa", undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - "New Delhi", undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - "Notes for a novel", undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - "Notes for novel - formal + thematic issues", undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Mostly blank notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Mostly blank notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Subseries B: Collage Notebooks and Sketchbooks
    Contains collage notebooks and sketchbooks, some of which includes Indiana's photography.
    - "Collage Book 1982" (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - School Agenda Collage Book, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Collage and Sketchbook, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Collage and Photography Book, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - "Tapper Zookie Lives On / This is My Album of Wasted Space", undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Series III: Correspondence and Legal Documents
  The correspondence series consists of personal and professional correspondence. Personal correspondence includes letters and postcards from figures including musician and poet Patti Smith and artist Valie Export, among others. Professional correspondence consists of publishing contracts and rights agreements with HarperCollins and other publishing companies. Also included is the report of the court examination of Indiana in his lawsuit against The Bar. Some postcard correspondence is contained in the Flyers and Visual Materials Series [Series IVA] as part of Indiana's flyer and program scrapbook. A poster from the Patti Smith correspondence is located in the Oversize series.
  - Personal Correspondence (1981-1999) (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Personal Correspondence (2000-2005 and undated) (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Patti Smith Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Valie Export Correspondence, 1981-1998 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Professional Correspondence, 1988-2004 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Court Examination: Lawsuit Against The Bar, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 95)
- Series IV: Flyers and Visual Materials
  - Subseries A: Flyer and Program Scrapbook
    Consists of the contents of a scrapbook, organized by Indiana, of programs and flyers for events or performances by himself and others. Some postcard correspondence is also included in the scrapbook. Also included are materials not associated with this scrapbook: one folder of event flyers and a flyer for the 1980 Times Square Show, the latter being in the Oversize series [Folder 124].
    - Roy Cohn/Jack Smith program, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Rent Boy postcard, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Digne Meller Marcowicz picture postcard with message, undated (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Three Films by Cameron Jamie with Live Music by The Melvins program, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Casino Paradise theater program, undated (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Ingrid Caven debut party invitation, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Jo by Cameron Jamie flyer, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Ingrid Caven Theatre de L'Europe program, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Roy Cohn/Jack Smith Programs (2), undated (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - The Theatre of Jack Smith flyer, undated (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - "Life of Roman Polanski (1)" photo, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - ...And That's How the Rent Gets Paid, Part IV by Jeff Weiss flyer, undated (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Jackie Curtis as Frances Farmer photo, undated (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - "Life of Roman Polanski (2)" photo, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Indiana and Duncan Smith "Diamonds" performance postcards (2), undated (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Taylor Mead "Merry Xmas to Gary" photo, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Alligator Girls Go To College program, undated (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Curse of the Dog People and Phantoms of Louisiana program, undated (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - "The Art Critic: A Temporary Job" lecture flyer, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Three Films by Cameron Jamie program (2nd copy), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Group photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Andrew Cunanan evidence photo, undated (Box 3, Folder 117)